白天很热
The day was hot,
但似乎夜晚温度降的很快
but the night turns chilly fast, it seems, for the time of year.
对于这个时节来说  后天我们就能到卡普阿
Day after tomorrow, we shall be in Capua
你就能在又大又暖和的房子里睡觉了
and you will sleep in a good warm house.
即使是山羊皮也有自己的优点
Though goatskin has its virtues.
现在好了 成了自己领土上的难民
Here we are, refugees in our own land.
我们不是难民 我们是在转移
We are not refugees. We are maneuvering.
就像你说的，我们在转移
As you say, here we are maneuvering,
那个暴君却占据了罗马
while the tyrant sits in Rome.
没错，在我自己的帐篷里
Yes, in my tent,
我可以熟睡的像个孩子一样
I sleep sound and deep as a child.
可能今晚不是  对不起让你受打扰，
Though perhaps not tonight.  I'm sorry it bothers you.
他很快就结束了
He'll be finished soon enough.
昆特斯对此比较有诀窍
Quintus has a knack for this kind of thing.
希望如此
Well, I hope so.
我不知道你儿子昆特斯和我们一起
Your son Quintus, I did not know he was with us.
从布林迪西出发，今早到的
Arrived this morning from Brindisi.
这样好多了
Ah,that's better.
我发现尖叫声真是很差的调味料
Screaming makes poor sauce, I find.
昆特斯虽然有他的缺点
Quintus has his faults,
但他很忠诚而且毫无畏惧
but he is loyal and fearless.
对于一个父亲来说不能要求再多了
Afathercannotaskmore.
我从来没听过，也没想过其他方面
I've never heard nor thought otherwise.
那只狗终于招供了
The dog confessed at last.
你脸上有血，去洗
Torn up good and red.  Blood on your face. Wash yourself.
多里奥在哪里？ 金子又在哪里？
Where is Durio? Where is the gold?
就像你怀疑的那样，他把多里奥杀掉了
He killed Durio as you suspected.
然后拿了金子沿着弗拉明大道往北走
And they took the gold north on the via Flaminia,
正好碰到了凯撒的巡逻兵
ran slap into Caesar's scouts.
两个罗马人，二十个尤比恩骑兵
Pair of Romans, 20 head of Ubian.
对我们的人来说太多了
Too many for our boys.
他们逃跑了，这些没用的垃圾
They ran, the filth that they are.
把金子留给了罗马侦察兵
Left the gold to the scouts.
这不可能 据我最近的消息
Can't be so. I've heard from Rome this last hour.
凯撒并没有得到金子
Caesar has not got the gold.
父亲，我的手下沃普总是能得到准确的消息
My man volpe always gets the truth, Father.
如果凯撒没得到金子 那肯定是他的侦察兵占为己有了
If Caesar does not have it, then his scouts must have kept it for themselves.
去找到这些侦察兵  我会的
Go find these scouts.  I will.
现在！
Now!
你看，现在形势已经在变了
You see, the tide turns already.
没有这些金子
Without the gold, Caesar will find Rome
凯撒会发现罗马更难被征服
a little harder to subdue.
没有金子，我们的日子也不太好过
Without the gold, we're not very well placed, either.
没有金子，他会开始使用暴力
Without gold, he will have to use violence.
一旦流血开始
Once he starts spilling blood,
人民会去向他复仇
the people will turn on him with a vengeance.
没有了人民，他就什么都没有了
Without the people, he has nothing.
戒严法现在生效
"Martial law is in effect
为了所有公民的安全
for the safety of all citizens.
三人以上的团体
Groups of more than three men
不允许在公共场合聚集
shall not congregate in public spaces.
宵禁开始生效
Acurfewis in effect.
任何人天黑以后在街道上出现
Any person found on the street after dark
会遭到审判
will be subject to summary judgment.
盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒万岁
Long live General Gaius Julius Caesar,
共和国的救世主
savior of our Republic."
次序！立定！
Order, halt!
天神朱庇特
Jupiter Optimus Maximus.
天神朱庇特 天神朱庇特
Jupiter Optimus Maximus. Jupiter Optimus Maximus.
公民，请称呼你自己
Name yourself, citizen.
优利亚的盖乌斯
Gaius of the Julii,
名字是凯撒  请讲
called Caesar. Speak then.
我恭谦的请求进行占卜
I humbly ask that auguries be taken
罗马可能已经知道
that Rome might know
诸神赞同我的行为
that the gods favor my actions.
由于你全副武装的进入城市
You've entered the city under arms.
我必须警告你很少会有吉兆
I must warn you that seldom augurs well.
神知道我的意图是和平的
The gods know my intentions are peaceful.
人民也必须知道
The people must know it also.
那好吧
So be it.
占卜将会在第一个洁净清晨进行
Augurieswill betaken on the first clean morning.
当鸟儿飞翔的时候
Let the birds fly where they may.
怎么样，老乡？  惨着呢
How be, paisan? Miserable.
为叛乱辛勤工作的奴隶
Slave of a rebel.
至少还是成功的叛乱
A successful rebel at least.
陪审团还在外面 你们怎么样？
The jury's still out. And you, my child?
万分不幸，在给一个残忍的女人当奴役
For true misery, try bondage to a bloody-minded woman.
凯撒说今晚的宴会上不要贝类食物
This dinner tonight, Caesar asks no shellfish.
这个是来宾列表
Here is a guest list.
我希望你的女主人清楚 这个宴会给她带来的荣耀
I hope your lady is aware of the honor done to her.
她非常清楚
She's very aware.
事实上 凯撒的女主人将会是罗马的第一女士
Caesar's hostess is first woman  of the city, in effect.
除了凯撒的妻子
Excepting Caesar's wife.
卡尔普蕊娜 凯撒要求
Calpurnia. Caesar requires that she's still and handsome
她必须安分，漂亮，尊贵大方 没其它了
and dignified and... no more.
她就像雕像那样有型
She is a species of statue.
这个名单很奇特
A very fancy list of people.
每一个留下来的贵族都被邀请了
Every aristo and optimate left in the city.
他不会是准备把他们都杀掉吧？
He's not planning on killing them, is he?
我不那么想
I shouldn't think so.
我的女主人不喜欢意外
My mistress doesn't like surprises.
赛维莉娅- 为什么邀请她？
Servilia- why invite her?
他们之间还藕断丝连吗？
Can there still be something between them?
像她那样慌乱的老破鞋？ 肯定不是
A rattled old sandal like her? Surely not.
她还有点姿色
Some juice in her yet.
我不会让那个女人在我和凯撒之间掺合
I'll not let that woman get between me and Caesar.
为什么赛维莉娅也被邀请来参加晚宴？
Why is Servilia invited to the party?
优利亚的赛维莉娅 她为什么被邀请了？
Servilia of the Junii, why is she invited?
显然是因为她的儿子
On account of her son, obviously.
你把我叫醒就为这个？
For this, you wake me?
当然了 他需要布鲁图斯作为他象征上的朋友
Of course. He needs to keep Brutus as his symbolic friend.
仅此而已
That's all.
如果布鲁图斯成为他的敌人 我看上去就和他们在一起了
It would look ill with the people if Brutus were his enemy.
他们之间并没有爱情 仅仅是政治而已
There's no love there. It's just politics.
神啊，你这个女人能不能让我睡觉？
Dear gods, woman, would you let me sleep?
多米那，山羊睾丸
The goat's testicles, domina.
傻瓜，不是给我的 给屋大维
Not for me, fool, for Octavian.
去找得墨忒耳
Fetch Demeter.
亲爱的，快趁热吃了
Eat them while they're warm, my dear.
它能让你的阴茎长的像橡木一样  我宁可不要
It puts oak in your penis.  I'd rather not.
胡说，你必须吃
Nonsense, you must.
你现在长的越来越女性化了
You've been developing a distinctly feminine anima,
我不喜欢那样
and I do not like it.
我不过是个男孩 这太自然不过了--
I am only a boy. It is entirely natural--
当我外公你这么大的时候 没有一个女孩奴隶是安全的
When my mother's father was your age, there was not a slave girl safe.
我们优利亚家族的男人都是非常有男子气概的
The men of the Julii are masculine men. Now do as I say
现在听我的话把它吃了  我不
and eat them.  I will not.
你不吃了它别想离开这个房间
You'll not leave this room until you do.
得墨忒耳，今晚的宴会不要有贝类食物
Demeter, the banquet this evening,
还有确保鳗鱼不要烧过了
no shellfish. And be sure the lampreys are not overcooked.
煮到能杀掉它们就不要再烧了
Boil them long enough to kill them, no more.
我还在等
I'm waiting.
那才是我的儿子
That's my brave boy.
弟弟  嗯？
Brother.  Hmm?
是不是妈妈找人把格雷毕斯杀掉的？
Did Mother have Glabius killed?
当然不是
Of course not.
你确定？
You're sure?
我不能证明，但我想应该是的
Well, I cannot prove a negative, but I'm sure as can be.
你以神的名义起誓？
You swear on Jupiter's stone?
我以神的名义起誓
I swear on Jupiter's stone.
如果确实
If she did,
如果确实是她杀了他的话
if she did kill him,
以复仇女神的名义，我会用牙齿把她的喉管咬开
by the furies, I'll open her throat with my teeth.
在纳波，我能开十次这样的宴会了
In Narbo, I can buy 10 feasts for this.
纳波不是到处是尸体和士兵吗？
Narbo isn't full of corpses and soldiers,
正派人因为太害怕都不敢出门
and decent people too scared to come out of their houses.
如果你不介意我这么说的话
No time to throw a do if you don't mind me saying.
我不开个宴会就没法开始做生意，是不是？
I cannot start a business without a feast, can l?
今天是吉日，而且非常安全
Today is auspicious, and it's perfectly safe.
我记得上回苏拉的士兵还在的时候
I remember the last time when Sulla had soldiers in the city.
血都可以用来刷墙了  凯撒不是苏拉
Blood, you could paint houses with it.  Caesar's not Sulla.
他宣布了戒严法 是为了和平而不是流血
He's declared martial law, not to spill blood, but to keep the peace.
等着瞧吧，是不是？
We'll see, won't we?
我向谷神和酒神乞灵 你不会失望的
I invoke Ceres and Bacchus, you'll not be dissatisfied.
你为我找只猪，我就帮你办宴会
You find me a pig, and I'll make you a feast,
即使是在地狱里，如果需要的话
in Hades, if need be.
照样收费  那个油商的老婆缪莎
And charge according.  Musa, the oilman's wife,
在她葬礼上用了海螺而不是牡蛎
served whelks instead of oysters at her womb funeral,
没人会让她忘记那一切
and nobody would let her forget it.
在街上嘲笑她
Laughed at in the street.
神圣的门神啊，我们把这个宴会献给你
Divine Janus, we offer this feast to you.
我恭谦的乞求你能对我们宽厚
I humbly beg that you will be gracious
对我和我的家展现你的仁慈
and merciful to me and my house,
你会向这个从今天开始的商业冒险微笑
and you will smile upon this new business venture
I begin today.
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯 尊贵的马克·安东尼想要召见你
Lucius vorenus, his honor Mark Antony orders your presence.
现在？  当然不是，难道是明年？
Now?  Of course not. Next year.
乌瑞纳斯，我亲爱的同志
vorenus, my dear comrade.
你手里没了血迹斑斑的长剑 我都认不出你来了
Barely recognize you without a bloody sword in your hand.
卡托，你可以走了
Off with you now, Cato.
很有趣，是不是？
Amusing, eh?
卡托  就像你说的
Cato.  As you say.
你当然不会感到有趣
Of course you don't all find it amusing.
那么…
So...
你的平民生活过的怎么样？
how is civilian life treating you, huh?
目前为止还不错，长官
Well enough so far, sir.
对了，当然了
You know, of course,
由于你逃跑，我可以将你钉在十字架上
I could have you nailed to a cross for desertion.
我没有叛逃 我的服役结束了
I am no deserter. My time was served.
我坚守了我的誓言
I abided my sacrament.
这是你…
It is you that...
这是为什么？
It is I that what?
一旦越过卢比肯河 罗马人就不再是士兵而是公民了
Once over the Rubicon, Romans are citizens, not soldiers.
我就不能再做之前做过的那些事了  傻瓜
I could not legally do other than I did. Foolish.
就像被斗篷蒙蔽了眼睛的牧师一样
Like a priest blinded by a cowl.
自从罗马成立…
Since the founding of Rome--
算了吧，乌瑞纳斯，绕了我
Oh, please, spare me the founding, vorenus.
事物总是在变的
Things change.
生活是水，而不是石头
Life is water, not stone.
那我想我会被淹死
Then I suppose I will drown.
你难道看不见你心中宝贵的共和国
Do you not see that your precious Republic
已经湮没很久了吗？
has long since died?
你看不见凯撒正把罗马从废墟中拯救出来吗？
Do you not see that Caesar is trying to save Rome from ruin?
我不觉得
I do not see that.
够了
Enough.
那么什么样可怜的贸易
Andwhatwretchedtrade
是你想从事的？
is it you intend to follow then?
从高卢进口货物 奴隶，软糖和酒
Imported goods from Gaul. Slaves, truffles, wine.
就这些东西？  一个杂货商？
That sort of thing.  A grocer?
像你这样一个战士
An honest fighting man like yourself
清点箱子
counting cartons,
乱记帐目
scribbling accounts?
你会发疯的  可能吧
You will swift go mad.  That may be.
我需要你，乌瑞纳斯
I need you, vorenus.
凯撒需要你
Caesar needs you.
军团里没有别人比你得到更多的尊重
There is no better man in the legion, none more respected by the men.
在前面我们有艰苦的战斗  针对罗马人的艰苦的战斗
We have hard fighting ahead.  Hard fighting against Romans.
血就是血
Blood is blood.
你真的想让十三军团的战士们
Would you really have the 13th
在没有你的情况下，批甲戴盔？
fasten their crest without you?
你要回军团来
You come back to the legion,
你会变的完美
you shall be inducted into the Evocati as a prefect.
在第一等级中，你还能得到奖赏
Of the first grade, with a signing bonus.
好比…
Say, uh...
一万塞斯特斯？
10,000 sesterce.
我选择了这条路 无论如何我都会走下去
I chose this path. I will follow where it leads.
乌瑞纳斯，你伤我的心了
You grieve me, vorenus.
你深深的伤害了我
You grieve me deeply.
算了，你走吧
Go on. Off with you.
日安，公民
Good day, citizen.
乌瑞纳斯
vorenus...
下次再看见你，我可能就不会这么友善了
next time I see you, I may not be so kind.
上面说什么？
What does it say?
不是很确定
It's not certain,
不过我可以看出你的秘密很安全
but I'd say your secret's safe.
不确定？
Not certain?
征兆混在一起
The signs are mixed.
那会怎么样？
What good is that?
告诉我你想掩盖什么
Tell me what it is you're hiding
我便能更准确地告诉你结果
and I can be more precise.
其中有一个孩子
There's a child involved.
一个男孩？
Amalechild?
婴儿？
The baby.
算了吧
Never mind. Best leave it.
随便你
As you please.
不过如果能帮到你的话，
If it's any help,
上面显示, 你丈夫会变的很富有
it does say your husband is going to be rich.
就像一个大富豪
Rich as Croesus.
总算还有点什么，是不是？
Well, that's something, isn't it?
谢谢你
Thank you.
好了，完成了
Good. Done.
水
Water.
我八年前看上去如何？
What did I look like eight years ago?
和现在一模一样
Just the same.
八年  八年
Eight years.  Eight years...
在粗糙的高卢妓女中间
of leathery Gallic trollops.
他最后是什么时候见过一个真正的女士？
When did he last see a real lady, hmm?
而且是如此漂亮的一个
And such a beautiful one?
鲜花  盛开的？
Flowers.  In bloom?
给每个这些官员的书记员五万
50,000 to each of the magistrate's clerks.
这么多？
So much?
我要把他们的忠诚彻底买断 而不是不断的去续约
I wish to buy their allegiance outright, not lease it.
要让他们签字
Have them sign for the money.
那么给次级执政官多少？
And how much for the sub-praetors?
零
Nil.
当他们听说书记员拿了多少钱 他们会过来乞讨的
When they hear how much the clerks got, they'll come begging.
这样会让我们没有任何资源来维持这个城市
And leave us penniless without means to run the city.
我们必须杀掉一些富人然后拿走他们财产
We must kill some rich men and take their money very soon,
否则井水很快就会耗干的
else the well will run dry
很快
very soon.
杀戮是毫无必要的
I plan on killing no one unless absolutely necessary.
找个贵族的策略，来点意外  毫无疑问
Afine novel strategy, an element of surprise no doubt.
晚点再听你的唠叨
Later you may nag me.
我相信这是合适的
I believe this is appropriate.
没错，亲爱的
Exactly right, my dear.
华丽，但不过分
Regal, but not excessively so.
真是个好的开始 如果没人来的话
Fine start to a business this'll be if nobody comes.
别担心，他们会来的
Don't worry. They will come.
或许我该听你的再等等
Maybe I should have waited as you said.
他们会来的
They will come.
记得，当他们来的时候
And mind now, when they do come,
试着偶尔笑一下
try to smile occasionally.
别向他们咆哮
And don'tbarkatthem.
这是谁？
Who's this?
伊拉斯特斯·弗尔曼 记得吗？ 我们尊贵的客人
Erastes Fulmen. Remember? Our guest of honor.
建筑贸易，火灾保险，橄榄
Building trades, fire insurance, olives.
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
Lucius Vorenus.
内奥比
Niobe.
感谢你们能光临，尊贵的邻居
Thank you for your coming, honest neighbor.
我知道在这样的日子里能来很不容易
I know it can't be easy on such a day.
来几个士兵又怎样？
What's a few soldiers, eh?
菲利斯，我的妻子
Wife, Phyllis.
请
Please.
请坐，先喝两杯酒  好的
Sit down and take a cup of wine.  I will.
有点渴了，呵
Thirsty road, eh?
姐姐
Sister.
你没事吧？
All right?
都很好，别担心
All's right. Don't worry.
谢谢  这不会是我小巧的莱得吧？
Thank you.  This can't be little Lyde.
好久没见了  你好，卢西尔斯
Surely not. Long time, eh?  Salve, Lucius.
这是我丈夫，伊万德·普契洛  欢迎，伊万德
This is my husband, Evander Pulchio.  Evander, welcome.
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯，我很荣幸  谢谢你们送的猪
Honored, Lucius vorenus.  Thank you for the pig.
所有店都关门了 为了这点肉我们可以尽情欢呼了
With all the shops shut, we would have whistled for meat.
很高兴能帮到忙
Happy to be of service.
非常感谢你能邀请我  这是我的荣幸
Thank you so much for inviting me.  My pleasure.
我的荣幸，赛维莉娅
My pleasure, Servilia.
我坚持说你必须要来
I insisted you come.
不管你遇到什么样的不幸
Whatever misfortune befalls you,
我们依然是朋友，对吗？
we're still friends, neh?
我得承认，她有个很好的帮她化妆的奴隶
She has a good cosmetics slave, I'll grant you.
但是作为凯撒的情人？ 荒谬
But a lover for Caesar? Absurd.
请为高级执政官让路 盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒
Make way for the pro-consul Gaius Julius Caesar,
维纳斯的儿子
Son of venus,
高卢军团的最高统治者
Imperator of the Gallic Legions.
退后致礼
Stand aside and open up.
别戏弄我了，我不过是你的叔叔盖乌斯 把头抬起来
Please, you mock me. It's only your Uncle Gaius. Lift your heads.
所有的人都把头抬起来
All of you, lift your heads.
我亲爱的侄女
My dear niece.
尊敬的叔叔
Revered uncle,
欢迎回家
welcome, welcome home.
优利亚的赛维莉娅 非常荣幸
Servilia of the Junii, a pleasant honor it is.
非常高兴
Delightful.
这是我的荣幸
Your pleasure is mine.
我非常遗憾你的儿子不在这里
I am very sorry your son is not here with you.
我也一样
I'm sorry also.
希望你能原谅他的缺席
I hope you will forgive his absence.
他永远是你的朋友
He is ever your friend.
我完全理解
I understand completely.
请向布鲁图斯传送我最诚挚的敬意
Please send Brutus my best regards
我保证他永远都不会有机会
and assure him he will never have reason
对我们之间的友谊后悔
to regret our friendship.
不管是谁向其他人效忠过
Nor will any of you, regardless of where your allegiances
都既往不咎
may have lain in the past.
有武器吗？  没有，长官
Any weapons?  None, sir.
你们从哪里来的？  从安特纳姆来
Where you coming from?  Come from Aternum, dominus.
做什么贸易？  收集尸体，研磨骨头
In what trade?  Corpse collectors, bone grinders.
总体上说做死人生意的
Dead business in general.
那你们真是来对地方了
You've come to right place then.
他们是谁？
What people are they?
是锡西厄人，长官 他们不说我们的语言
Scythians, chief. They don't speak our language.
那你们过去吧
On your way then.
让我们进去！
Please let me in!
你！
You!
告诉你的手下，离高贵的妇女们远点
Tell your brutes to stay away from decent women.
我会的
I'll do that.
这些你从高卢人那抢来的东西可真不错
Fine bit of plunder and rapine you made off them bloody Gauls,
我打赌  我不会抱怨的
I bet.  I'll not complain.
这种动荡的时代还真容易挣钱
Handy to have cash in these uncertain times.
男人不能离开自己的产业去逃跑
A man can't flee with his house and fields
如果他选错阵营的话
if he's chosen the wrong side.
没错
True.
你认为谁会最终取胜？
Who do you reckon will come out on top?
这很难说
It's hard to say.
你会不会希望是你自己的人？
You'll be hoping it'll be your man though, eh?
如果你说的是凯撒的话，他已经不是自己人了
If you mean Caesar, he's not my man anymore.
所以你的战利品
So your spoils,
我期望你会出租你的收益
you'll be lending the proceeds, I expect.
我不会的
I won't.
我把这里买下来因此不会有额外的现款
I am buying back this insula so I'll not have spare cash.
我打算把这儿的贸易空间用来做进口生意
I plan to take over the trading space for an import business.
主要是奴隶  奴隶？
Slaves mostly.  Slaves?
听着
Well, listen,
我有一些朋友
I have friends,
很好的朋友
bona friends.
如果你需要帮助，你来就找我
If you want any help, you come to me, eh?
再来点酒，甜心
More wine here, sweetie.
那儿还有些很不明智的人
There are even those unwise men
说出现在南部象限仪上的一只白鸟
who say that a white bird in the southern quadrant
既不指示什么也不否定什么
is neither indicant nor negation.
这真是我们时代里野蛮的革新
Such are the barbarous innovations of our day.
野蛮
Barbarous.
我们可能会成为叙利亚人
We might as well be Syrian.
我非常同意  叙利亚人，没错
Point to pommel, I agree.  Syrians, indeed.
甚至是锡西厄人
Scythians even.
作为首席占卜师，我很高兴听到你这么说
As Chief Augur, I'm gratified to hear you say so.
据说你的观点都很时髦
It was heard you are a man  of modish opinion.
哦，那些都是流言
Oh, that's pure scandal.
我坚信宗教是我们杰出的教士们的职责
I believe that religion is the province of our worthy priests.
像我这样的战士最好不要去干涉
Mere soldiers like myself best not interfere.
那真是很令人高兴
That's very gratifying.
屋大维，别像个穷人那样坐在那里
Octavian, don't sit there like a prole.
说一些有意义的话  我没有什么好说的
Say something witty.  I have nothing such to say.
你知道我不能说，母亲
You know I cannot talk small, Mother.
那你好了
You then.
念些诗歌如何？
Some poetry, neh?
她能很快的背诵这些东西
She can rattle off pages of the stuff.
“去往地狱很容易
"Easy it is to go down into Hell.
死亡的大门总是敞开着
The gates of death are ever open.
困难的是要重新爬回”
To climb back out again, that's the difficulty."
有点阴暗，亲爱的，不过没关系
It's a touch dark, my love, but never mind.
她刚失去她的丈夫
She lost her husband, you know.
最好把你姐姐带走
Best get your sister gone.
我告诉过你让她来是个错误
I told you it was a mistake to let her come.
我必须得让她来，否则看上去会很奇怪
I had to let her come. It would look odd if she wasn't here.
去跟伊万德说一下，好不好？
Speak to Evander, will you?
屠夫，该把你老婆带回去了
Butcher man, time to take your wife home.
她不想走F
She doesn't want to go.
最好让她走
Best make her go then, eh?
是时候回家了  不
Time to go.  Not yet.
我喜欢这儿  是时候走了
I like it here.  Time to go.
放开我，亲爱的  莱得，不要这样
Let me go, my love.  Lyde, please.
放开我
Let me go
否则我会告诉我们勇敢的战士一个非常好的故事
or I'll tell our brave soldier such a good tale.
你要害死我们？ 这是不是你想要得？
Kill us all? Is that what you want?
我爱你，可你为什么不爱我？
I love you. Why don't you love me?
对不起
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
莱得，不要这样  我是你的妻子
Lyde, please.  I'm your wife.
我们有协议的！ 你向神发过誓的！
We had an agreement! You vowed to Persephone.
你发誓你会保持沉默
You vowed you would hold your peace!
我难道没有保持沉默吗？  如果我的丈夫--
Have I not held my peace?  If my husband--
你的丈夫是个瞎子！
Your husband is a blind fool!
你听到了吗？ 他又瞎又傻
Did you hear me? He's a blind fool!
放开我！ 放开我！
Get off me! Get off me!
放开我！
Get off me!
妻子？
Wife?
卡西里亚
Caecilia.
能不能告诉我
Tell me,
卡西里亚现在怎么样？
how is Caecilia?
她很健康，谢谢  很好
She's healthy, I thank you.  Good.
我想起来我忘记了你妻子上个生日
I recall I forgot her last birthday.
她的生日？  我知道这是我的错
Her birthday?  Remiss of me, I know.
她也许能原谅我如果我能再送给她些礼物
Perhaps she would forgive my rudeness were I to send her a gift.
真的，那没必要
Really, that's not necessary.
为女人挑礼物真的很难
Hard to find the right gift for a woman, neh?
这个人喜欢的，又被别人亲篾
What one loves, another scorns.
可能她会接受一点钱
Perhaps she would accept some money.
这个注意不错
There's an idea.
十万塞斯特斯怎么样？
100,000 sesterce, say?
那真是非常慷慨
Oh, that's very kind of you.
但是恐怕我的妻子的品位是很昂贵的
I'm afraid my wife is a woman of expensive tastes.
最好的女人都是这样的
The best women often are.
十五万
1 50,000.
如果我允许的话她甚至会让她的奴隶们穿上丝绸
She would dress her slaves in silk if I would let her.
她每天早晨都吃牡蛎
She eats oysters for breakfast daily.
她应该小心一些
She should be most careful.
很多人都会被牡蛎噎到
People often choke on oysters.
二十万
200,000.
那真是非常慷慨，我愿意说那是
That is a very generous, and I may say,
一件非常合适的礼物
appropriate gift.
她会深深的欠你一个人情的
She would be under great obligation to you.
她只要能想到我就不欠我了
To think well of me would be her only obligation.
她总是能想到你
She's always thought well of you.
她能继续这么做不会是件不道德的事情的
It is not unethical she continue to do so.
我们能理解对方
We understand each other.
把这记下来
Make a note of it.
二十万给首席占卜师
200 to the Chief Augur.
那个笨蛋猜他自己是个财主
Thinks he's Midas, the loon.
Go past the cloth works.  Thank you very much.
明早第一件事我们得去拜访门神的牧师们
We'll go to the priests of Janus tomorrow first thing,
希望今天的事能得到宽恕 这很昂贵，但是…
and have the day absolved. It's costly, but--
征兆就是征兆，不好的时候它们总是会来
An omen is an omen. And this is as bad as they come.
没必要往里面扔钱
No point throwing money at it.
你姐姐和她丈夫以后不允许再来了
Your sister and her husband can never come here again.
就照你说的吧
As you say.
不能够屈服
Must not bend.
你好啊，平民
Salve, pleb.
百夫长卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯？
Centurion Lucius vorenus?
你是谁？
Who asks?
尊贵的昆特斯·庞贝阁下
His honor Quintus Pompey.
你最好对此有个解释
You best have good reason for this insult.
你这只狗最好快点告诉我金子在哪里？
Tell me where the gold is, and quick about it, dog.
什么金子？ 说点有意义的话
What gold? Speak sense.
这样够不够有意义？  不够
Sense enough?  Not near.
我再问一遍，什么金子？  他是不是很顽固？
I ask again, what gold?  Stubborn is he?
我猜这个婊子是你老婆
This trollop we can assume is your wife.
抓住她
Hold her.
我没法说我不知道的事情
I cannot speak what I do not know.
我不知道任何关于金子的事
I do not know of any gold.
你知道的很清楚我是在找国库黄金
You know very well I seek the treasury gold
你从我父亲手下那里抢去的
you took from my father's men.
我没有从任何人那里抢走金子 你被误导了
I took no gold from any man. You are misinformed.
误导
Misinformed.
你难道不是第十三军团侦察兵的头么？
You are not chief of scouts 13th legion?
曾经是
I was.
上周你是不是截住了一辆装运谷物的马车
And last week, did you not stop a grain wagon
在弗拉明大道上？  是的
on the via Flaminia?  We did.
赶车的人是由士兵伪装的
Driven by soldiers disguised.
是那些士兵把马车丢下的
We chased the soldiers and left the wagon.
你就没想过要看看里面是什么？
You never thought to look inside?
我们有命令在身，没有时间
There was no time. We had orders.
我所知道的是，你们的马车还在那里
Your wagon is still there for all I know.
撒谎。割了她的喉咙
Lies. Cut her.
快点，把它给我
Come on, give it to me!
来给我亲爱的朋友卢西尔斯造点噪音
Boys, a clamor for my beloved friend Lucius.
怎么看上去这么忧郁？
Why so glum and gloomy?
他是谁？
Who's this then?
尊贵的昆特斯·庞贝阁下，特鲁里亚舰队的指挥官
His noble honor Quintus Pompey, commander of Tyrrhenian fleet.
海王星苦难的根源
Neptune's scourge.
哦，海王星苦难的根源
Oh, Neptune's scourge.
他们在寻找一马车的国库黄金
Looking for a wagon of treasury gold.
国库黄金？
Treasury gold?
听上去真令人兴奋
How exciting!
别再测试我的耐心，乡巴佬
Do not test my patience, peasant.
快滚吧，笨蛋
You be off now, short ass.
别忘了带走这些渣滓
Take these scum with you.
我的看法是
The way I see it,
我们把昆特斯丢到台伯河中淹死
we put little Quintus here in the Tiber right off,
然后找辆四轮马车偷偷的去埋金子的地方
get us a wagon, sneak out to where the gold's buried.
把金子挖出来，然后像风一样赶到海岸
Dig it up, ride like Zephyrus for the coast,
趁着第一波潮水去西班牙  我在试着思考
and get the first tide for Spain.  I'm trying to think.
那样做有什么不好？  怎么不好？
What was wrong with that?  What's wrong?
即使我不荒谬到
Even if it were not a monstrous sin
去偷罗马的神圣财产…
to steal sacred property of Rome...
我不是不知道么，是不是？
I wasn't to know, was l?
…然后躺在担架上穿越大街
...you then ride through the streets on a litter,
不停的叫喊，唱歌，广播你的偷盗行为
shouting and singing and broadcasting your theft
给所有的人知道
to all and sundry.
到明天日出的时候，所有的罗马人都会知道 你做了什么，还有你在哪里
By sunrise, everyone in Rome will know what you did and where you are.
就在这里，我的房子里
Here, in my house.
那我们该怎么办？
So what's to be done then?
你必须把金子交出去
You will have to give it back.
如果你现在直接去找凯撒
If you go direct to Caesar now,
把庞贝的儿子作为甜点带给他 他可能会对你额外开恩
bring him Pompey's son as a sweetener, he might show mercy.
交出去？ 我不这么认为
Give it back? I don't think so.
这不是建议 这是命令
That's not advice. That's an order.
我来和你分享神送来的礼物…
Here's me come to share a god-sent gift--
命令！
An order!
真该死！ 我的家被人入侵了
Damn you. My home was invaded
因为你，我妻子差点被杀掉
and my wife near killed on your account.
好吧
All right.
你会和我一起去，是吧？
But you'll come with me though, eh?
这是你自己搞出来的乱子 你自己去处理
This is your mess. You get yourself out of it.
那好吧
Fine then.
我这就去
I'll be off then.
祝你好运，长官
Good luck to you, sir.
原谅我，我很快就回来
Forgive me. I will try to return swiftly.
对不起，亲爱的
Excuse me, my dear.
波罗，你这个无赖
Pullo, you scoundrel.
你这次做了什么？
What have you done now?
尊贵的阁下…
Your honor, uh...
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯说我应该来找你…
Lucius vorenus said I should come to you and--
士兵，别急
Easy, soldier.
这个是谁？
Who is this?
庞贝的儿子，昆特斯
Quintus, son of Pompey.
还真是的！
So it is!
昆特斯，我的老伙伴
Quintus, my old cock,
看到你这样我可真开心
how good to see you so.
解释吧
Explain.
好，是这样的，阁下
Well, it's like this, your honor.
他来找他们的金子
He, this one come to find the gold.
什么金子？
What gold?
是庞贝的手下从国库偷走的金子
The gold that Pompey's boys stole from the treasury, sir.
庞贝没有得到金子？
Pompey does not have it?
他没有，阁下
He doesn't, sir.
现在请恕我对您的不尊敬
Now I meant no disrespect,
如果我知道金子是来自于国库的话
and had I known the gold was from the treasury,
我宁可不去碰它 但是当时这个女孩在…
I'd not have touched it. But there was this girl here, sir--
别管这个女孩了 挑重点说
Never mind the girl. Speak to the point.
金子在哪儿？
Where is the gold?
它非常安全，阁下
It's all safe, sir.
我把它埋到树林里去了
I buried it deep in the woods
从弗拉米尼亚斯大门出去几里远
a couple miles from the Flaminian gate.
感谢上天
Thank you.
你会为此付出代价的
You will pay for this!
显然你能做的更棒  先放过他
Surely you can do better than that.  Leave him be.
很抱歉我们这样见面，昆特斯
I'm sorry we meet like this, Quintus.
我对你的父亲和家庭都无比的尊敬
I have only deep respect for your father and his family.
去死吧，你们这些狗杂种
Kiss my ass, you traitorous dog.
他真是个傲慢的小家伙呢，是不是？
Elegant little fellow, isn't he?
你不需要害怕 你的生命还属于你自己
You need not fear. Your life is yours still.
我把你送回给你父亲
I'm sending you back to your father
还有一份停战协议  停战协议
with an offer of truce.  A truce?
安静
Quiet.
你疯了吗？
Are you run mad?
When we have them on their backs in the sand?
安静
Be quiet.
一个基于很好条件的停战协议
An offer of equable truce on good terms.
如果暴力继续的话
If violence continues,
这将不是我，而是你父亲 和他的盟友们的所作所为
it will not be my doing, but that of your father and his allies.
我父亲不需要停战协议
My father needs no truce.
再过两个满月就能看到 你被钉死在议事大厅里
Two full moons will see you on a spike in the Forum.
你这可怜虫  把他抬到马上去
You wretch!  Put him on a horse.
你这个淘气的女人
You naughty woman.
从来告诉我凯撒对你还有这份热情
Never told me Caesar had such a passion for you.
不是这样的
Not so.
我看到他看你的眼神了
I saw the way he looked at you.
就像公牛看到了欧罗巴
Like the bull that tupped Europa.
我不能责怪他
I can't blame him.
这么的…
Such...
美丽
beauty.
这样的美
Such beauty.
太友善了
Too kind.
太过友善了
Far too kind.
凯撒对我没有偏好
Caesar has no inclination to me.
我对他也一样
Nor I to him.
还这么的谦虚
And such modesty.
卡尔普蕊娜，她是不是很漂亮？
Is she not beautiful, Calpurnia?
而且一点都不淫荡
She has none of the goatishness
通常她这个年纪的女人都会有的
one normally sees in women her age.
可能她喝了什么秘密药水了吧
She has some secret potion perhaps.
我觉得你有点轻佻了
You are attempting levity, I believe.
很抱歉如果我不能再纵容这样的谈话
Forgive me if I do not indulge in such talk.
你肯定会后悔让他逃命的
You're sure to regret letting that one live.
He has a malevolent spirit.
再我完成之前还会有很多亡灵的
There's many left undead I'll regret before I'm done.
带上波罗去找金子吧
Take Pullo and retrieve the gold.
军团士兵波罗
Legionary Pullo.
你是个小偷
You are a thief.
一个愚蠢的，不合格的小偷
A foolish, incompetent thief.
但是你以前的服役很不错
But you have served us well in the past.
所以我们嫁妆你的愚蠢是诚实的表现
So we will pretend your foolishness is a species of honesty,
并且判定你无罪
and let you go unpunished.
事实上，我们会给你点小小的奖励
In fact, I think we shall reward you.
我不想为了财富而争论不休
I do not like to quarrel with Fortune,
显然你已经是她的宠物了
and clearly she's taken you for a pet.
当你找到埋藏地点的时候 给他一百个金币
When you find the trove, give him 100 gold pieces.
谢谢，阁下
Thank you, sir.
如你所愿
As you wish.
对了，安东尼，不要对我的判断产生疑问
By the by, Antony, never question my judgment
特别是在我们的敌人面前
in the presence of our enemies.
你的记忆力很好，所以你将会记得
You have a good memory, so you will remember that.
我会的  解散
I will remember.  Dismissed.
士兵，马！
Men, horses!
快点！  出发！
Quick about it!  Forward!
你为什么皱眉头，小猫头鹰？
Why do you frown, little owl?
马克·安东尼说的很有道理
Marc Antony speaks sense.
战略上讲停战协议不是非常的合适
Truce now does not seem tactically correct.
这要看具体条件
Depends on terms.
你给庞贝了根本接受不了的条件
You offer terms that Pompey cannot accept
但是西赛罗和元老院能接受
but Cicero and the Senate can.
真机灵
Swift--
等等，有人在看着呢
Hold up, dominus, there's people watching.
把我们带到没有人去的地方
Sir, take us somewhere none can see us.
他怎么了？ 他被下毒了吗？
What's in him? Is he poisoned?
他有疾病，过一会儿就会好的
He has the Morbus Comitialis. It will pass in a moment.
快，关上门
Please, dominus, shut the door.
Should we not fetch a doctor?
不会吧
We should not.
无论发生什么，都不能让人知道他的痛苦
At all costs, he cannot have his affliction known.
没有人会跟随一个
No one will follow a man
被太阳神诅咒了疾病的人的
whom Apollo has cursed with the Morbus.
向天起誓，你不会向任何人说起这件事
vow to Orcus, never speak of this.
你没事吧，丈夫？
Are you quite well, husband?
没什么
Nothing serious.
来
Come.
阿提娅，我觉得很累了 我想我们该离开了
Atia, I'm growing tired. I think we shall leave you.
哦，好的
OH, well
当然，如你所愿  晚安，亲爱的
As you wish, of course.  Good night, my dear.
你晚上过的愉快吗？
Did you have a pleasant evening?
是的
I did.
你的侄女阿提娅真是太客气了
Your niece Atia is most polite,
首席占卜师作了很多关于宗教的评论
and the Chief Augur made many edifying remarks on religion.
抱歉我不能和你马上一起回家
I regret I will not be coming home with you immediately.
But you're not well.
Really, I am quite recovered.
I have urgent business with my marsupial clerks.
晚上还有公务？ 这不是很恰当
Business at night? It is not proper.
不恰当，但是必须的 我必须准备好离开这个城市
Not proper, but necessary. I have to be ready to leave the city
一旦庞贝拒绝和和约 马上就要开始追击他
and pursue Pompey as soon as he refuses truce.
他会拒绝吗？
He will refuse?
我认为是这样的
I believe so.
母亲，怎么了？
What's wrong, Mother?
我很孤单
I'm alone.
我孤单一人
I'm all alone.
他说什么？  荒谬！
What does he say?  Ridiculous!
他说什么？  没什么
What does he say?  Nothing.
不值得重复
Nothing worth repeating.
但是他提出停战了？
But he offers a truce.
什么条件？
On what terms?
和那个渣滓停战？ 你是女人？
Truce with that scum? Are you women?
我要让他们被狗强奸
I'll have them raped by dogs!
安静 出去！
Silence. Get out!
原谅他吧 他被凌辱了
Excuse him. He's been ill-used.
但他是对的，我们不会停战
But he is right. There can be no truce.
当然不
Of course not.
但是凯撒没有要求很多
But Caesar does not ask for so much.
法律豁免权，共同裁军  我必须放下武器？我？
Legal immunity. Mutual disarmament.  I must disarm? I?
我是罗马合法的执政官 他是个罪犯
I am lawful Consul of Rome. He is a criminal.
没有什么是共同的
There is nothing mutual in it.
他可能是个罪犯，但是他拥有整个城市
He may be a criminal, but he has the city.
我们必须解决这些问题  事实是，他是个叛徒
We must deal with facts.  Fact is, he is a traitor!
让我们公平的说吧
Let us be fair.
执政官，他已经是非常的友善了
Consul, he has been remarkably peaceable.
他既没有杀害你的盟友也没有入侵你的家产
He has not killed your allies or violated your property.
我们必须认真地对待这份提议
We should look on this offer seriously.
你难道没看见他的阴谋吗？
Do you not see his stratagem?
他是要分裂我们
He is trying to drive a wedge between us.
停战协议至少能为我们赢得时间  昆特斯说的很对
A truce would buy us time at least.  Quintus is right!
你们真是女人！
You are women!
傻瓜
Fools.
告诉我你爱他
Tell me you love him.
告诉我然后我就会离开
Tell me that and I will go away,
我永远不会再回来
and I will never come back.
我爱他
I love him.
看在我的孩子们的灵魂上， 我爱他
On the souls of my children, I love him.
泰特斯·波罗！真是令人高兴
Titus Pullo, what joy!
他们最终绕了你？  是的
They let you go alive then?  They did.
乌瑞纳斯在哪儿？
Where's vorenus?
他去了门神神殿补过忏悔了
He's gone to make amends at the shrine of Janus.
你认识伊万德·普契洛吗？ 我姐姐的丈夫
You know Evander Pulchio, my brother-in-law, my sister's husband.
伊万德
Evander, you say?
祝你健康，士兵
Good health, soldier.
你也一样
And you.
喝点水吗？
Will you take water?
好的  你先坐
I will.  Sit you down.
朱庇特主神给了我们征兆
Great Jupiter, graciously give us clear signs
在我能看到的范围里
within the bounds I have traced.
征兆很不错
The auguries are good.
翻译:TLF字幕组